<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Credo resurrectionem carnis a tractate on the  eleventh article of the Apostles Creed / by W.H. Esquire sometimes of Peter-house in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Hodson, William, fl. 1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13552.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S5090</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38160589</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38160589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29260</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03426)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29260)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1928:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Credo resurrectionem carnis a tractate on the  eleventh article of the Apostles Creed / by W.H. Esquire sometimes of Peter-house in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Hodson, William, fl. 1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-192 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.P. for N. Bourne, and are to be sold at this Shop, at the South Entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: P. 192.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹² (-A₁), B-H¹².</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, torn, and with print show-through; pages bound and filmed out of order.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apostles' Creed.</term>
               <term>Resurrection.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29260:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29260:1"/>
            <p>Credo Reſurrectionem CARNIS.</p>
            <p>A Tractate on the eleventh Article of the Apoſtles Creed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> W. H. <hi>Eſquire ſometimes of Peter-houſe in Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>skull with wings</figDesc>
               <head>SPES ADDIDIT ALAS.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E. P.</hi> for <hi>N. Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the South Entrance of the Royall Exchange, 1633.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:29260:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29260:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Credo Reſurrectionem Carnis.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Creed in generall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> ſaid of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall</hi> Learning,<note place="margin">Origen. Hom. <hi>7.</hi> in Exod.</note> may not unfitly be applyed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29260:3"/> to theſe Breviaries and Epitomes of Holy Writ, <hi>like the Iewes Manna, they fall downe in round and ſmall cakes, yet afford good nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> Like rich Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, they carry worth in every ſparke, and in theſe little maps is contained a world of matter.</p>
               <p>As thoſe <hi>decem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> the ſhort Law of the Decalogue, is a patterne of all duties to bee done; As that <hi>Oratio quotidiana,</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours lips, is the curious
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29260:3"/> Archetype, &amp; maſter-peece of all prayer, the common place, the originall copie, the platforme of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts to bee made; So the Apoſtolicall Creed is a plaine and abſolute ſumme of all holy Faith.</p>
               <p>It is called in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh the Creed, from the firſt Word, <hi>Credo; quia omnia credenda;</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius;</hi> whoſoever will bee ſaved, before all things it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that he hold the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke faith; which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29260:4"/> faith except every one keepe whole and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, without doubt he ſhall periſh everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly. It is called A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall, becauſe it ſummarily conteines the chiefe and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall points of religion handled and propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the doctrine of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Other confeſſions are received not as new, but as paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and expoſitions, and enlargements for the better clearing of this: for as there is but one Faith, ſo but one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29260:4"/> Creed; as the foure Goſpels, are indeed but one Goſpel; ſo the Apoſtolicall, <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> and <hi>Nicen</hi> Creed, are but one in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>This of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles hath ever been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted in the Church moſt ancient, and of greateſt authority; which although it be not Protocanonicall Scripture; yet is it the key of Scriptures, <hi>&amp; medulla Scripturarum,</hi> the pith of the whole Bible. Here have I an ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dful of holy flowers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29260:5"/> which are called from the ſeveral beds of that ſpacious garden of the ſacred Scripture; here is collected into one faire body, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and ſweetneſſe of all thoſe divine my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries which either lie hidden or ſcatterd in the volume of holy writ. This is that <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulus Iudex</hi> the little Iudge in matters of quarrell about religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for what doctrine ſoever is contrary to the Analogie of faith in theſe things, ought and muſt bee rejected.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29260:5"/> If a foole ſay in his heart, there is no God, If a Iew deny Chriſt, If an Epicure beleeve not a life everlaſting, If a <hi>Cain</hi> deny the remiſſion of ſinnes, or a Corinthian the Reſurrection of the fleſh: All theſe croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Articles of our Chriſtian faith, the Church rejecteth them, God condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them, And they fearefully periſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his mercy to recall them.</p>
               <p>The matter or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Creed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth,
<list>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:29260:6"/>
                     <item>1 God,</item>
                     <item>2 Church,</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>Firſt God</head>
                  <item>1 The Father and our Creation, Article 1.</item>
                  <item>2 The Son &amp; our Redemption, in the <hi>6.</hi> next Art.</item>
                  <item>3 The Holy Ghoſt Article 8.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Secondly, it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Church in the 4. laſt Articles, which is more fully deſcribed by her
<list>
                     <item>Properties
<list>
                           <item>1 Holy Article 9.</item>
                           <item>2 Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke. Article 9.</item>
                           <item>3 Knit in a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Article 9.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:29260:6"/>
                     <item>Prerogatives.
<list>
                           <item>In the ſoule, remiſſion of ſins, Art. 10.</item>
                           <item>In the body, reſurrection, Art. 11.</item>
                           <item>Body &amp; ſoule, everlaſting life, Art. 12.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe bee the twelve ſignes in the Zodiake of our faith, through which paſſeth Chriſt Ieſus, the Sun of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes. O never may the clouds of infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty darken or eclypſe his beames.</p>
               <p>Theſe twelve Articles
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29260:7"/> are ſo neceſſary and ſo lincked together, that hee that denyeth one by conſequent denyeth all, becauſe that of any one ſo denyed, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our faith is ſtraightly inferred, He that with <hi>Marcion</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth the Humanity of Chriſt, may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily convinced to deny the paſſion of Chriſt, becauſe the God-head is impaſſible; &amp; he that with <hi>Ebion</hi> denyeth the Deity of Chriſt, may with the like facility bee convinced to deny
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29260:7"/> the Reſurrection of Chriſt, becauſe the manhood onely never had beene able to raiſe it ſelfe from the dead.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4.</note> And hee that deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Reſurrection of Chriſt, cannot beleeve his Aſcenſion; becauſe the Apoſtle telleth us, (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.9.) that hee which aſcended, is the ſame which deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded firſt into the lower parts of the Earth.</p>
               <p>By this manifeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, may we plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee the connexion of theſe Articles. If yee deny one, yee deny all;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29260:8"/> and if yee renounce any one, yee cannot be ſaved.</p>
               <p>But I will not take a large ſurvey in a ſmall plot, Its a good rule to be obſerved by booke-writers which a great maſter in oratory hath preſcribed, <hi>ut titulum legant,</hi> to reade the title of their bookes, and often to aske them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what they have begun to handle. From this maine ſea, I will therefore ſtrike into a little channell: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drunke of the brooke in the way, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29260:8"/> given a taſt of the Creed in generall, I deſcend to this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Article, which is rhe ſubject of our following Treatiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:29260:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Each terme in this ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Article remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, from the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of which is infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the immortality of the Soule, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of the riſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of the body.</head>
               <p>IN our precedent Chapter we ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the dependancy of one Article with another, and that to deny any one of theſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29260:9"/> principles, is the next degree to infidelity. Wee may farther illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate this truth by this Article of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</p>
               <p>Hee that beleeves not this, beleeves all other things in vaine; for if there bee no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from death, then can he receive no reward of his faith. Nay I will take the note a little higher; He that beleeves not this, beleeves no other Article of his Creed; for (as our Engliſh Poſtiller hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29260:10"/> from <hi>Eraſmus</hi> apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) The whole Creed in groſſe, &amp; every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell thereof, argueth a reſurrection. If there bee a God Almighty, then hee is juſt, and if juſt, then another reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in another world; If a Ieſus Chriſt who is our Saviour, then muſt hee diſſolve the workes of Satan, ſinne and death. If an Holy Ghoſt, then all his holy Temples which have glorified him here, ſhall bee glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of him hereafter. If a Church which is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29260:10"/> holy, then a Remiſſion of ſins, a Reſurrection of the body, a life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
               <p>Thus doe wee ſee how this <hi>Primarium E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelii caput,</hi> this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant Article pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth all the reſt: how it is, <hi>Nexus Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culorum omnium,</hi> the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knot on which all other links of holy Faith depend. By this hand is religion held up by the head. This is the anchor of our hope, the reference of our faith, the certainty of our ſalvation, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29260:11"/> the very dore of the Kingdome of heaven.</p>
               <p>From this mine ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth another treaſure: it is worth our obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, how this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is placed betweene the Article of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, and the other of Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life; teaching us, that then only the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body is a benefit, when Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins goeth before, &amp; eternall life followeth after: for as the Reſurrection is <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes Fidej,</hi> ſo eternall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29260:11"/> life is <hi>Corona Fidej.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this, as in each parcell of the Creed are two maine things obſervable.</p>
               <p>Firſt the Act, which is to beleeve, therefore <hi>Credo</hi> muſt be applyed to every Article, <hi>Pides eſt tota copulativa.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the object, which is the enſuing Article. In the Act, is the perſonality, which is faiths poſſeſſive <hi>[E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go]</hi> I beleeve; This was <hi>Iobs</hi> Creed, <hi>Scio quod Redemptor n<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> I know that my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer liveth. I muſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29260:12"/> (ſaith one) put all men in my <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> only my ſelfe in my Creed; My prayer muſt bee like the penny, which <hi>Peter</hi> found in the fiſhes mouth, with which Chriſt bid him pay tribute <hi>pro me &amp; te;</hi> I muſt pray for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, beleeve for my ſelfe. No mans faith can do mee good, but mine owne; for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beleeve by an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney, nor be ſaved by a proxie. When doubting <hi>Thomas</hi> fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his faith at his fingers ends, then did hee cry
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29260:12"/> out with an holy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation, my Lord, and my God, (<hi>Vt bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſima ſit abſolutiſſima confeſſio,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bullinger</hi>) for hee did utter that in two words which is the contents of the two Teſtaments, and ſumme of all ſummes of Faith and holy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe. That living car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſe (whom formerly wee mentioned) hee that was even poore to a proverbe, was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular faith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 19.26.</note> I ſhall ſee God in my fleſh, <hi>id eſt</hi> (as it is excellently
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29260:13"/> gloſſed on) I in my fleſh ſhall ſee God, or, <hi>Videbo Deum in carne, h. e. Deum incarnatum,</hi> I ſhall ſee God, having taken fleſh on him. If I have this faith in particularity, and can apply things generall to mine owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, then God even my God ſhall give me his bleſſing: <hi>Et non eſt haec ſuperbia Elati, ſed confeſſio non ingrati.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the Act, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move our meditations to the object: and here wee will firſt explaine thoſe two Emphatical
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29260:13"/> termes
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Carnis.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For in theſe models &amp; ſummaries of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrine, there is weight in every word, we muſt therfore here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in imitate the finers of pure gold, <hi>Qui non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum auri maſſas tollunt, verum &amp; bracteolas par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas,</hi> that make uſe not only of the wedge, but even of the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt foile or rayes, that their mettall caſteth.</p>
               <p>Reſurrection is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly a riſing againe upon a fall taken: for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29260:14"/> this praepoſition <hi>[Re]</hi> (as it hath beene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">B. of Wimo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> by a pious and learned Father of our Church) doth ever im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, not only <hi>Againe,</hi> but <hi>Againe,</hi> as it were upon a loſſe, not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond onely, but a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond upon the failing of the firſt; as Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a buying againe upon a former alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Reconciliation upon a former falling out;<note place="margin">Orthod. fid. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> Reſtitution up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a former attainder; Reſurrection upon a fall taken formerly: to this ſuites well the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29260:14"/> definition of it given by <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Reſurrection is a ſecond quickening or ſetting up againe of that which firſt fell; <hi>Reſurget quod prius ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this word then [Reſurrection] we do find the ſtrength and ſinewes of an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If the body riſe it muſt firſt fall: in this is implicitly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up a confeſſed truth; That all men muſt dye the firſt death; <hi>Debemur morti
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29260:15"/> nos noſiraque,</hi> to dye is as true, as good a debt as any the world knowes; for the levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which debt (as one excellently, and with a ſilver pen) there is an extent upon all mankind; and a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute recorded by Saint <hi>Paul, Statutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt omnibus ſemel mori;</hi> This a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree not to bee rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, a debt not poſſible to be declined.</p>
               <p>Here might I have ſtore of rich cloath, to apparel my lines with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but leſt the hemme ſhould be bigger than
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29260:15"/> the garment, I have taken no more than what is ſuitable to my purpoſe.</p>
               <p>My ſecond obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, that in this common cognizance of our faith, in this Article of my Creed, I do not ſay at large, I beleeve a Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but more ſtrictly, more expreſſely thus, <hi>Credo reſurrectione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> I beleeve the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the fleſh <hi>[Carnis ſcilicet non Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae]</hi> This word Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection doth properly belong to the body;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29260:16"/> the body that fals muſt riſe.</p>
               <p>To thinke that our ſoules ſhall ſleepe in duſt, as our bodies doe till the laſt doome, is but a dreame of the Anabaptiſts (the ſpawne of the ancient <hi>Arabicks) Ne in ſomni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quidem cadit anima cum corpore, quomodo er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go in ueritatem mortis cadet, quae nec in imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ejus ruit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian:</hi> and experience tels me, that my ſoule while it is now like the Arke of God, <hi>In me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio pellium</hi> in theſe wals
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29260:16"/> of fleſh, hath her owne working and lively o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, even then when the Publican ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſteth my body, while my ſenſes are impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the bands of ſleepe.</p>
               <p>For the mind of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a reſtleſſe thing,<note place="margin">Of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the Soule.</note> and though it give the body leave to repoſe it ſelfe, as knowing it is a mortall and earthly part, yet it ſelfe being a ſpirit &amp; therfore active and indefatigable is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in motion, it hath no riſe at all from this clay; It ſleepes not in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29260:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> a living body, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhall not ſleepe in a dead body, it is made of an everlaſting nature; As Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall decrees have an end without a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſo the ſoule of man hath beginning without an end. It hath beginning to live it ſhall have no time to dye. There is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a death of the Soule, not that it ceaſeth to bee, but when it ceaſeth to bee righteous; <hi>Habet &amp; anima mortem ſuam cum vitâ beatâ caret, quae
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29260:17"/> vera animae vita dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> conſonant to this is that genuine and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per interpretation of thoſe words of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt; what will it profit a man to gaine the whole world, and loſe his ſoule: <hi>Perde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re animam,</hi> ſaith the gloſſe, <hi>Eſt non ut non ſit, ſed ne male ſit;</hi> for the ſoule being immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall is capable of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, either Felicity, or Miſery, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever life: it liveth, yet it never ceaſeth to live.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:29260:18"/>
               <p>I have briefely ſet down the riches of the obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ariſe from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of theſe two termes; both which I find compriſed in one verſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoule in grave,</hi> [there's the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the ſoule] <hi>nor ſuffer the holy one to ſee corruption</hi> [there's the Reſurrection of the body.] This <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> knowing before (ſaith the Scripture) ſpake of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſt, the accompliſhment of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29260:18"/> which prophecy is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repeated in the new Teſtament;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 2.31. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.35.</note> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit <hi>David</hi> after hee had ſerved his time, by the Counſell of God, hee ſlept, and was layd with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and ſaw corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yet by the vertue of an inſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into that Chriſt, whoſe ſacred body the Lord preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the leaſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet apprehends a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hope of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of his owne fleſh to Immortality, and aſſures himſelfe,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29260:19"/> that God will not give him over to that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which ſhall ſeize on him in the grave, that his dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall not miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor vaniſh away in rotteneſſe, but bee rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againe in glory.</p>
               <p>This meditation leades me by the hand to treate of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Reſurrection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pertinent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the ſeries of our diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:29260:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Chriſts Reſurrection ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Angels, by his owne apparitions, by the fulfilling of the Prophecies, his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ours.</head>
               <p>THE glorious reſurrection of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was firſt proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by an Herauld from Heaven, ſo all
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29260:20"/> the Evangeliſts teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy. <hi>Sonuit de ſepulchro vox laetitiae,</hi> never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was heard ſuch newes from the grave, but at that time, when an Angell was the preacher; his Sermon, Chriſt is riſen; his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> and other devout wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <p>To diſcourſe at large of thoſe celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and immortall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, comes not within the compaſſe of my walke, yet thus much briefly and to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:29260:20"/>
               <p>Angels however they ſtill behold the face of our Heavenly Father, yet they are but his houſhold ſervants, his pages of honor which hee ſends on his holy errands, the ſacred tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Saints, the guard of Gods elect, the watch-men over the wals of the new Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, chaplaines in ordinary to the King of heaven, Meſſengers &amp; Miniſters attending about his Throne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting his pleaſure, alwayes in readineſſe to make knowne his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29260:21"/> will unto Man.</p>
               <p>When God brought forth his firſt begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sonne into the world, he ſayed, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him all yee An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and ſo they did; when the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, oreſhadowed by the Holy Ghoſt, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her divine bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then within her wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, an Angell appeared unto <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to juſtify the innocency of the Mother, and the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Sonne; when hee was borne the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels told the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſheepheards,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29260:21"/> and that with an <hi>Ecce</hi> too, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. when <hi>Herod</hi> ment death to the Babe for the name of a King, an Angell revealed the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and willed him to fly into Aegypt with the child, and ſo, <hi>Populus Aegypti qui fuit perſecutor primogeniti,</hi> became <hi>cuſtos unigeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti:</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Herod</hi> was dead, the Angell bid <hi>Ioſeph</hi> returne againe into <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> When Satan left tempting him the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels came and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto him; when his ſoule was excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29260:22"/> ſorrowfull unto death, the Angels at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to comfort him; &amp; when his body was to bee raiſed from death, an Angell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends to draw away the curtaine, while our Lord came forth of his bed-chamber; an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell roles away the ſtone which his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries had laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his grave; an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell is the firſt that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the glad tidings of his reſurrection.</p>
               <p>The truth of this Angelicall aſſertion, was ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by Truth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29260:22"/> it ſelfe; for what the Angell preached unto the women, what the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reported to the Apoſtles (for in this Article were they firſt catechiz'd by the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker ſex) our Saviour makes good by his manifold apparitions, being ſeene at ſundry times by ſuch, who were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp; ideo</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, witneſſes cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen before of God for that purpoſe, as the Apoſtle affirmes in his little Creed to <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> Acts 10. wherein is a ſynopſis or ſumme
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29260:23"/> of the chiefe points of holy beliefe.</p>
               <p>Concerning the
<list>
                     <item>Doctrine, <hi>verſe</hi> 36, 37.</item>
                     <item>Miracles, <hi>verſe</hi> 38.</item>
                     <item>Life, and Death, <hi>verſe</hi> 39.</item>
                     <item>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>verſe</hi> 40, 41.</item>
                     <item>Comming to iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>verſe</hi> 42.</item>
                  </list> of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>What <hi>Peter</hi> there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites to his Auditor, his new convert, his <hi>Cornelius,</hi> what <hi>Paul</hi> elſewhere to his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29260:23"/> was all fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, <hi>Per os Propheta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> by the mouth of the holy Prophets; for this is ſure &amp; conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, Nothing was done by Chriſt which was not foretold, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was foretold, which was not done. So that there was an <hi>Oportet,</hi> a forceable reaſon that he ſhould riſe againe, <hi>Vt implere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> that the Scripture might be fulfilled, his Reſurrection being, as <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, <hi>Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum omnium promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionum,</hi> the <hi>Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29260:24"/> eſt,</hi> the period, the accompliſhment of al predictions.</p>
               <p>We may farther illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate this if we looke on our Saviour (as he was ſeene by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in a viſion) as a King,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.2.</note> as a Prieſt, as a Prophet; walking amongſt the midſt of the Angels, as a King; cloathed in white as a Prieſt; and with an inkhorne han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging at his girdle as a Prophet; And here likewiſe ſhall wee find an <hi>Opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet,</hi> that his
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Propheticall,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sacerdotall,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Regall,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Offices,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29260:24"/> each of them implyed a proofe of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
               <p>Firſt, let us conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him as a Prophet, even the Prince of Prophets. When the Angels at the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher ſayed unto the women, why ſeeke yee the living among the dead? He is not here,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk</hi> 24.6.</note> but hee is riſen: hee addes to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber how he ſpake unto you, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee was yet in <hi>Galile,</hi> ſaying: The Sonne of man muſt be delivered into the hands of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; be crucified,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29260:25"/> and the third day riſe againe. It is remember <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not what only, but how, not the matter, but the manner; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that: He will keep his word, though he die for it, &amp; though he dye for it, hee will riſe againe the third day, to keep it to a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute. The very <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of his reſurrection is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined; He roſe the third day, &amp; that early too. When God was to give ſentence upon man for ſin, he ſtayed till the heat of the day was over; but upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29260:25"/> day, being to preach remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins, he roſe betime, while it was yet darke. It was the Love of God, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection to his Church, which he had ſo lately, &amp; ſo deerely bought, made him riſe ſo ſoone, and appeare ſo often the ſame day to diſtreſſed ſoules. In all my Creed there is no other circumſtance of Time, but this, of all the Actions of Chriſt for mee there recorded, onely this Action of riſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, though of all
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29260:26"/> the moſt difficult, yet it is to bee beleeved with the circumſtance of time &amp; no other; to ſhew; that the doubt and difficulty, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probability, in reſpect of meanes bee it what it will, yet whenſoever my Saviour promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, hee keepeth it, as well as whatſoever he hath promiſed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as his prophecy, ſo his prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood inforced his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; How could it appeare that the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation was cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the law fulfilled,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29260:26"/> God pacified, if hee had not riſen againe; If the debt had not bene taken off by the ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it would have lyen ſtill upon the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall; If Chriſt had not riſen from the dead, wee ſhould ſtill be yet in our ſinnes, and our Faith ſhould bee in vaine. But wee know that our high Prieſt with one offering hath conſecrated for ever, them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14.</note> The powerfull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of this paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on endureth for ever; being the La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be ſlaine
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29260:27"/> from the beginning of the world, and blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as it were, to the worlds end. <hi>Aron</hi> and his ſucceſſors were but onely forerunners of Chriſt, who is the end of the Law, and for this cauſe called, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos accedens,</hi> or <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniens,</hi> a Prieſt added to the Prieſts, a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſummating the prieſthood of the old. As there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Prieſt before, had the love to ſacrifice himſelfe for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo never had any
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29260:27"/> the power to revive that ſacrifice hee once killed: but our high Prieſt Chriſt Ieſus, had love to lay downe his life and power to take it up againe; by the firſt hee ſhewed himſelfe to bee the Sonne of man after the fleſh; by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hee was declared mightily to bee the Sonne of God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.13.</note> As he could not but dye, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken on him a body of death; ſo hee could not but live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, becauſe that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was, <hi>Vitae ſacrarium,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:29260:28"/> the veſtry and chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell wherein life was preſerved.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, as hee was made to be a Prophet like <hi>Moſes (Act.</hi> 3.22.) a Prieſt like <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech (Pſal.</hi> 110.4.) ſo alſo a King like <hi>David (Luke</hi> 1.32.) God will give him the throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> and hee ſhall rule over the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>Hee was a King by birth, <hi>ſimul natus, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul Caeſar,</hi> ſo the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men teſtifyed of him <hi>Math.</hi> 2.2. And hee
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29260:28"/> was a King at his death, ſo <hi>Pilate</hi> wrote his inſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> though in the narroweſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, Ieſus of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth King of the Iewes, <hi>Ioh</hi> 19.22. But to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the Meſſias for a temporall Prince was the Iewes perpetuall dotage, the Apoſtles tranſient errour, <hi>Math.</hi> 20.21. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.6. Lord wilt thou at this time reſtore the Kingdome to Iſrael. Of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall royalty hee had ſo little a ſhare, that his chaire of eſtate, was the Croſſe; his crowne
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29260:29"/> made of thornes, his ſcepter a reede; and for a <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple gave him a <hi>Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fige.</hi> But <hi>Qui ſubijt, ſubegit,</hi> hee that did undergoe, did over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; and as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſweetly, <hi>Qui agnus extiterat in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione, factus eſt Leo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectione;</hi> Hee that ſtood as Lambe at his Paſſion to take away the ſins of the world; became a Lyon at his reſurrection to ſpoile all principalities and powers, and to make an open ſhew of them,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29260:29"/> 
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.15. Then did he manifeſt himſelfe a moſt victorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror over all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, then did hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the keyes of death, and hell, then did hee breake the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head, and made all knees bow to him in heaven, earth, and under the earth. And now being raiſed from death, hee dyeth no more, death hath no more power over him; for this is his Epithite (as the beholder and pen-man of that reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which hath as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29260:30"/> many myſteries,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.18.</note> as words hath ſet it downe) He that was dead, and is alive, and liveth for evermore.</p>
               <p>From hence ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth naturally matter of
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Confutation,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Conſolation.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, this doctrine of our Saviours Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is a ſufficient condemnation to all Iewes, who (as we have formerly noted) doe ſtill looke for another Chriſt: for why ſhould they not beleeve their owne Prophet. They ſaid the <hi>Meſſias</hi> ſhould
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:29260:30"/> ſuffer, Chriſt ſuffered all things ſo as they were propheſied; Who then can be the <hi>Meſſias</hi> but hee, in whom all the prophecies are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth the wicked errour of <hi>Corinthus,</hi> who taught, that Chriſt ſhould not riſe till the generall Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; But as <hi>Iob</hi> confuted the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſpeech of his wife, with a <hi>Loqueris ut inſana mulier;</hi> ſo <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> worthily ſaith of this hereticke, <hi>Stoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:29260:31"/> eſt &amp; ſtolidorum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter.</hi> I will not take up the graves of the <hi>Chiliaſts,</hi> or <hi>Millena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> in their very name may we reade their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, but their groſſe ſuperſtitions &amp; aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall for me bee buryed in ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Thus having melted the droſſe from the ſilver mettall, let us ſee what fruit wee can plucke from theſe branches.</p>
               <p>Chriſt, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> is become the firſt fruites of them that ſlept;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20.</note> Hee is the firſt ſheafe of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29260:31"/> by &amp; from which all the whole crop of the dead Saints re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive vertue. At the time of our Saviours Reſurrection, ſome few eares that were then ripe, and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the whole harveſt ſhall bee carried into everlaſting barns. The Eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt ſpeaking of it ſaith; that many bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Saints which ſlept aroſe; All the dead did not riſe, but many, &amp; thoſe Saints too; the generall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection is reſerved to the laſt day; this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29260:32"/> was a pledge and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of it. As many roſe with him, ſo ſome before him, but all the Reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which we read of in former times were wrought in the figure and vertue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes Sonne, and <hi>Iai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> daughter, came forth of their graves, or were, recovered to life, <hi>Mortui ſed morituri:</hi> But Chriſt was the firſt that roſe, <hi>Cum victoria Mortis;</hi> that roſe to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, never to viſit the grave againe.</p>
               <p>This aſſureth us of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29260:32"/> our Reſurrection,<note place="margin">Chriſtus e<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> typus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum.</note> for as the head muſt riſe before the members; ſo the members are ſure to follow the head; if the head bee above water, there is hope for the whole body; if the roote hath life, the branches ſhal not long be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; the firſt fruites being reſtored to life, all the reſt of the dead are entitled to the ſame hope: for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is not only <hi>Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pex &amp; exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plar,</hi> but alſo, <hi>fidej iuſſor,</hi> yea <hi>Chirogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phum
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29260:33"/> noſtrae reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis;</hi> ſo that he that did riſe will raiſe. Theſe two reſurrections are inſeparable. Thus did that great Champion of the Church, who (as a Father ſaith) <hi>Priuſquam natus erat Dominus Redemptorem ſuum vidit à mortuis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurgentem.</hi> Thus did <hi>Iob</hi> excellently argue, when from,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 19.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Scio quod Redemptor,</hi> hee infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Scio quòd ego, &amp;c.</hi> I am ſure that my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer liveth, and I ſhall riſe againe at the laſt day: for, <hi>eadem
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29260:33"/> catena revincta eſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti Reſurrectio &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some divines af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme (from the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Bonaventure</hi>)<note place="margin">D. Boys poſtil. pag. 868.</note> that the yeere wherein our bleſſed Saviour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe from the dead, ſhould, according to the Law, have beene the yeere of Iubile: which Feaſt, was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Lord to be celebrated every fiftieth yeere for theſe cauſes.</p>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Why the Iubile was celebrated every 50. yeere.</note> that they might keepe a right Chronology and reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29260:34"/> of times: For as the Grecians did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute their times, by the number of <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piades,</hi> the Romans by their <hi>Luſtra,</hi> ſo the Iewes by their <hi>Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, that a true diſtinction of their Tribes might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; becauſe then La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds returned to their owners in their proper Tribe; and ſervants to their owne families; hence was it called <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile,</hi> from a word, which in the originall ſignifieth, <hi>deduxit,</hi> or
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29260:34"/> 
                  <hi>produxit,</hi> becauſe it brought men backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to their eſtate.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, hee inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted theſe <hi>Iubiles,</hi> that they might bee a type to them of their full deliverance by Chriſt, &amp; for this cauſe was it called <hi>Buccina reductio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> becauſe they blew with Rams-hornes, at this feaſt, in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance out of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</p>
               <p>And ſurely the <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le.</note> in old time did myſtically ſhaddow forth that Spirituall
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:29260:35"/> 
                  <hi>Iubile,</hi> which Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s enjoy under Chriſt; by whoſe blood, wee have not only a reentry into the Kingdome of heaven, which we loſt in the tranſgreſſion of our great Grandfather <hi>Adam</hi> which wee had formerly morgaged &amp; forfeited by our ſins: And this was happily ſignified by the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lits reentry upon their lands which they had formerly ſould; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the found of the Goſpell (which was in this Feaſt typed by the noiſe of the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets)
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:29260:35"/> is gone through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world.</p>
               <p>The Redemption of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eaſter Day.</note> is a yeere of <hi>Iubile,</hi> the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt is the chiefe day in the yeere yea, <hi>Regina Dierum,</hi> as <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſtiles it. All Chriſtians, herein i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitating the patterne of the bleſſed Apoſtle, in honour of Chriſts Reſurrection,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2.</note> obſerve their Sabbath on the eight day, which is the firſt day of the weeke, wheras the Iewes hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed their Sabbath upon the ſeaventh day
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:29260:36"/> which is the laſt day of the weeke. So that Eaſter day is the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of Sabbaths, an high and holy day, from which every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sunday hath its name; being ſo called, becauſe the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, aroſe from the dead this day.</p>
               <p>Chriſts appearing on the eight day, is not without a myſtery; wee labour ſix dayes in this life, the ſeventh is the Sabbath of our death, in which wee reſt from our labours;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:29260:36"/> and then being raiſed from the dead, the eighth day, Chriſt in his owne body, yea the very ſame body that was crucified, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward every man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his works.</p>
               <p>Happy then is that man, whoſe whole life is nothing els, but a Lent to prepare him againſt the Sabbath of his death, and Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:29260:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Arguments drawne from divers Attributes of God, as his Power, Mercy, Iuſtice, &amp;c. to confirme us in this Article of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</head>
               <p>AT my firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the ſchoole of faith in the very firſt Article of my Creed, I no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner reade that there is a God, but I learne withall that hee is Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:29260:37"/>
               <p>The doctrine of his Omnipotency, is the baſis and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Arch, on which is built our Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hereof proceeds all faith; becauſe wee beleeve with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, <hi>Quia po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens eſt,</hi> that God is able to doe all thoſe things which reaſon is not able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe the ignorance, or the not right underſtanding of this truth, is the cauſe that there bee ſo many <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleevers
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:29260:38"/> and misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers: Atheiſts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge of God; Infidels, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope or faith in God. It was our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours own Argument againſt the Sadduces, you erre not knowing the Scriptures,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 22.29.</note> nor the power of God, <hi>i. e.</hi> (ſaith the Paraphraſe) yee Sadduces doe erre groſſely &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nably, in this your miſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit of the reſurrection, &amp; the ground of your errour is your ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce both of the Scriptures, which have cleerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:29260:38"/> the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and of that Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent power of God, wherby is only this (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe impoſſible) worke. If with the men of <hi>Berea</hi> wee do ſearch the Scriptures, wee ſhall find, that before the Sadduces had any being in Iſrael, this hereſy of theirs was palpably convinced, with an example of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, even in <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> revived corps. Now the power that can raiſe one man, can raiſe a thouſand, a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a world. No power
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:29260:39"/> can raiſe one man, but that which is infinite, and that which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, admits of no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation.</p>
               <p>In the beginning the Word of the Lord was the ſeminary of all being: his will was his Word, and his Word was his deed. His <hi>Fiat</hi> and <hi>Fuit</hi> met together, his <hi>Dixit</hi> and <hi>Benedixit</hi> kiſſed each other. All at firſt was nothing, and from that nothing carne all: How eaſy is it then, for him to repaire all out of ſomething, who
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:29260:39"/> could thus fetch all out of nothing? How ſhould we diſtruſt him for our reſurrection, who hath approved his Omnipotency in our creation? Our remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der after death can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bee ſo ſmall, as our being was before the world, aſhes is more than nothing.</p>
               <p>The body, wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that is once cold in death, hath no more aptitude to a reanima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than that which is mouldred into duſt; only as it was Gods omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy to create
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:29260:40"/> man out of a ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that had no ability to produce the matter: ſo likewiſe it is the Prerogative Royall, to revive that duſt, to forme it into a new <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> to fetch a man a ſecond time from the earth, to live with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, when time ſhall bee no more.</p>
               <p>This Reſuſcitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead is one of thoſe foure keyes, which (the Hebrewes ſay) are in the hand of him, who is the Lord of the whole world. The Scripture makes
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:29260:40"/> mention of each of them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Clavis pluviae,</hi> the key of raine; the Lord will open to thee his good treaſure: <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Clavis cibatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> the key of food; Thou openeſt thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and filleſt every thing with thy plenteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.16.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Clavis ſterilitatis,</hi> the key of barreneſſe; God remembred <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi> and opened her Wombe: <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 30.22.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Clavis ſepulchro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:29260:41"/> the key of the grave; when I ſhall open your ſepulchers: <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.12.</p>
               <p>By all which places it is intimated, that theſe foure things God hath reſerved in his owne hand and cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Namely, Raine, Food, the procreation of children, &amp; the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of our bodies. For though at firſt hee made him, <hi>ex nihilo,</hi> out of nothing, yet he did not make him, <hi>ad nihilum,</hi> to returne to nothing; There may be a diſſolution of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:29260:41"/> ſoule and body, for a time, but there cannot bee an annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of either, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnited againe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for ever.</p>
               <p>As we have derived a maine proofe of the Reſurrection from the power of God; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may wee argue from his other glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and divine attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes: but becauſe I will not enlarge a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe into a volume, I will herein follow the Schoole-men who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all <hi>communiter ad
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29260:42"/> duo:</hi> his
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mercy,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iuſtice.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe be the two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Attributes which ſet all the reſt on work: theſe bee the two feete of God whereupon he walketh al his wayes.</p>
               <p>When God makes a covenant with his owne, it is an incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible &amp; everlaſting covenant,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.19.</note> therefore it is called a covenant of ſalt; to note the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of it. In this covenant are all the dead Bodies of the Saints, and the Lord forgetteth them not.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:29260:42"/> When <hi>Iacob</hi> we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t down to Aegypt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 46.4.</note> the Lord promiſed to bring him backe againe: but how did the Lord bring him backe againe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee died in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt? the Lord was with him when hee was brought out of Aegypt. So the Lord preſerveth all the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Saints,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.20.</note> and hee keepeth all their bones, yea even then when their bed is made in the duſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are within the covenant. It is ſaid of <hi>Ioſias</hi> (although hee
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:29260:43"/> was ſlaine in battle) yet he was gathered in peace to his Fathers, <hi>i. e.</hi> to the Spirits of his Fathers who enjoy peace; for hee was not gathered in peace in his body, for hee was ſlaine in warre. 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 35.</p>
               <p>In 22. of <hi>Math.</hi> and the 32. Chriſt ſaith I am the God of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> and the God of <hi>Iſaack,</hi> and the God of <hi>Iacob.</hi> God is not the God of the dead, but the living; Hee doth not ſay, I was the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:29260:43"/> 
                  <hi>Iſaack,</hi> and of <hi>Iacob;</hi> or I am the God of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> that once was: but as implying his owne eternall being, and the certaine being of thoſe holy Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, hee ſaith, I am the God of <hi>Abraham, &amp;c.</hi> Now God is not the God of thoſe that are not, and have no exiſtence at all, but of thoſe that have a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. So that hee will raiſe their bodies, or elſe he did, <hi>Dimidium tantummodò Hominem reſtituere,</hi> elſe hee were God but to one part
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:29260:44"/> of <hi>Abraham.</hi> But as his mercy is over all his works, ſo his works of mercy are over all his: His mercy extends both to ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and in the mercy of the moſt High they ſhall not miſcarry: Therefore ſhall God raiſe the bodies of dead men.</p>
               <p>But wee muſt not frame unto our ſelves a God all of mercy; but learne to ſing that compounded ditty of the Pſalmiſt, of mercy and Iudgement. Gods iuſtice is himſelfe as
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:29260:44"/> well as his mercy: As his mercy (which wee have already ſhewed) ſo likewiſe his iuſtice requires, that their muſt bee an univerſall reſurrection.</p>
               <p>If in this life (ſaith the Apoſtle) wee have hope in Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.15.</note> we are of all men moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. <hi>Paul</hi> indeed was at a, <hi>quotidie morior,</hi> every houre in danger to bee drawne to the blocke, every day dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ready to bee offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up for the name of his Lord and Saviour: But to what purpoſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:29260:45"/> did hee expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſuch variety of perils, if there were no reſurrection? Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is that man that either laboureth, or ſuffereth in vaine; Shal <hi>Paul</hi> beare in his body the markes of Chriſt Ieſus, and ſhall he not beare in the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the crowne of his glory? Shall the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer endure the heate of the day, and ſhall hee not at length receive this penny, his wages? <hi>Chriſtiani ad me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talla,</hi> was a uſuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but what
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:29260:45"/> made them digge ſo willingly in the mines? Surely they had a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure there which the Emperour knew not of, they had infinite more precious wealth from thence then hee: For the hope of the gaining a better life, is the perſwaſive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoricke againſt the feare of looſing this; <hi>Haec veſpera eſt, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt addi matutinam laetitiam;</hi> and then ſhal our birth be conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate when the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the morning are made one day.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:29260:46"/>
               <p>Theſe mixt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of contrary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, as a Croſſe and a Crowne, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Mortality and heaven, death and life, are ſtrong grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and ties to hold a Chriſtian and his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience together; It were iniurious to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of the meaſure, when we acknowledge the recompence; Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are the flowers of eternall felicity, and who would not willingly gather the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:29260:46"/> flowers for the fruits ſake.</p>
               <p>He that hewed tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber out of the rocke,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.6.</note> was knowne to bring it to an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t peece of worke: ſo was <hi>Ioſeph</hi> hewed in the ſtocks, and in the priſon, God brought him to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent peece of work, to make him Lord of Aegypt; Thus was Chriſt Ieſus hewed and ſquared on the Croſſe, with hammers, &amp; nailes, and ſpeares; of that excellent work ſee where he ſitteth at Gods right Hand,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:29260:47"/> Thrones, Powers, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, Angels ſubjected to him. And thus will God deale with the dead bodies of his Saints, which though they have bin perſecuted here, and the iron hath even en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into their ſoule, yet at length, they ſhal come out of their graues, like ſo many <hi>Ioſephs</hi> out of priſon: for Death like that Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Miſtreſſe hath only power over their coates, their upper gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, their bodies; and the grave like the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:29260:47"/> ſerpent is dieted and feedes on nothing but duſt. It is not ſo much the death of the body, as the corruption of the body, <hi>Mortalitas magis ſinita eſt quam vita.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Lord brought the Iſraelites to Canaan, he made them goe Southward into the mountaines, the South was a dry and barren part. Thou haſt given me a South land, give mee alſo ſprings of water, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 1.15. Thus doth God deale with his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:29260:48"/> in this life, hee ſheweth them great afflictions and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the South part, as it were at firſt, but afterward he bringeth them to the land that floweth with milke and hony.</p>
               <p>He that ſhall build his faith on this rocke, hee that doth thus, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere fidem in ſine,</hi> will <hi>ſupervolare crucen<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph o're the Croſſe, and with <hi>Iob,</hi> comfort himſelfe on the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill with a <hi>videbo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> and outface death with his Reſurrection,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:29260:48"/> in hope and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that glory, hee ſhall once enjoy with Chriſt. <hi>Benedictus ſic Deus,</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) Bleſſed hee God who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten us againe unto a liuely hope by the Reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt to an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance incorruptible, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It hath beene well obſerved, (by one of no vulgar Iudgement) how the Reſurrection is there placed, in the midſt betweene our hope and our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:29260:49"/> To hope before it, before the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, hope; but after to the inheritance it ſelfe, to the full poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion and fruition of it.</p>
               <p>So from the ſtate of hope, by the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (as by a Bridge) paſſe wee over to the enjoying our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>Before I ſhut up this ſtage, I muſt cleere a doubt, and remove an objection which hangeth on this thinge</p>
               <p>Some of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins have conceited,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:29260:49"/> that the wicked by corporall death ſhall utterly bee extinct, and that none ſhall come to Iudgement, but they ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; grounding their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.5.</note> The wicked ſhall not riſe in Iudgement: But here inſteed of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall milke of this text, they ſucke out the blood of miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation; And they which ſhall tenter and wreſt the Scriptures (which is a fault Saint <hi>Peter</hi> complaines of)
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:29260:50"/> with expoſitions and gloſſes newly coined, to make them ſpeake what they never meant muſt needs bring forth <hi>aut hereſim, aut phrene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim.</hi> If wee tread in the ſteps of the beſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, we ſhal find (as <hi>Hierome</hi> &amp; others ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) that this is not to be underſtood, <hi>Quod non furgent, ſed quod in judicio non reſurgent;</hi> Hee ſaith not that the wicked ſhall not riſe, but in judgement they ſhall not riſe; not riſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, faith Chriſt; as Felons
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:29260:50"/> whoſe fact being evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, are placed at the bar not ſo much to be convicted, as to bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned. Their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that like a Blood-hound hunts drie foote, ſhall ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them the ſent of their ſinnes, ſoe that the Lord Iudge ſhall not make any great inquiſition to find out their faults, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſentence.</p>
               <p>At that great aſſiſe ſhall wee all appeare (<hi>Nam oportet nos omnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>&amp; confuſi &amp; confiſi,</hi> both
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:29260:51"/> Chriſts confeſſors, &amp; his crucifiers, but the end of their Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhall bee diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; the one to glory, the other to ſhame: which was properly fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> two ſervants,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 40.</note> the Baker, and the Butler; both of them were taken out of priſon, but the one to bee reſtored to his office to miniſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee put to death. So ſhall both the godly and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked come out of their graves, the one, <hi>Rapi
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:29260:51"/> in occurſum,</hi> to meete their Saviour in the clouds, the other, <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti retrorſum;</hi> to be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned down to hell with all the people that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God.</p>
               <p>But I will not ſtraine this note. I have the rather touched upon it, becauſe it is one of thoſe, <hi>Quantuor nociſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> which wee ſhould ſtill have in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: for after death commeth judgement, whoſe forerunner is the univerſall Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
               <p>The day of death;
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:29260:52"/> and the day of doome are the two Pole-ſtarrs on which wee pilgrimes and travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers on earth ſhould fix our eyes. May my ſoule ſtill keep on this wing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10.</note> may my heart be like <hi>Daniels</hi> win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow which was open in his chamber toward Ieruſalem; may I oft repoſe my ſelfe on the roſe bed of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation; for they that never have any holy whiſperings with God, that never walk up to Mount <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor,</hi> into ſome retired
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:29260:64"/> place of meditation and prayer, (ſuch as <hi>Iſaacks</hi> field, <hi>Cornelius</hi> his Leads, <hi>Davids</hi> Cloſſet) carry their ſoules in their bodies, as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren did their money in their ſacks, and know not what Treaſure they have. And here for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode have I occaſion given to treate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:29260:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Of Sadduciſme and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereſies which flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſe this Article of the Reſurrection.</head>
               <p>SVperſtition and Atheiſme are the two extreames of Religion; the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes ran on the Rocke of the one, and the Sadduces ſunke in the Sand-beds of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:29260:65"/>
               <p>This groſſe errour of Sadduciſme crept into <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the high Prieſts themſelves, as <hi>Ioannes Hircanus;</hi> with his ſons <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naus</hi> the younger were of this Sect.</p>
               <p>To ſhew the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall &amp; occaſion of this hereſie, I muſt open an antiquity, and take up a ſtory, as I finde it already related to my hands. The Sadduces were ſo called from <hi>Sadoc,</hi> the firſt Author of this hereſie; this
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:29260:66"/> 
                  <hi>Sadoc</hi> lived under <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus Sochaeus,</hi> who not long after the daies of <hi>Nehemial</hi> was the chiefeſt Rabbin in the great Synagogue at Ieruſalem; this <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus</hi> gravely inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting his Diſciples, that they ſhould not be of ſervile mindes, or doe their duties for hope of reward: His Schollers hearing this deſired him to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound his mind more fully, whereupon hee added, that men muſt not expect the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of a good
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:29260:66"/> life in this world, but ſtay for it untill the world to come: To theſe words <hi>Sadoc</hi> a chiefe diſciple of his tooke exception, and ſaid, Hee never heard of any ſuch thing as the world to come; whereupon hee with his fellow <hi>Baithu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Apoſtates, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired to the ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Temple built upon Mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> and became principall Rabbins of the Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans. Amongſt them did <hi>Sadoc</hi> firſt broach his hereſie, and taught
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:29260:67"/> them that there was no Reſurrection of the dead; becauſe no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the ſoule and ſpirit, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently no judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come.</p>
               <p>Will you have a fuller relation of their impiety, ſhall I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of a Sadduce as I find it curiouſly pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled out? Caſtly our eyes on the Table of that counterfeit <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> where you have him lively ſet forth in his proper colours. In his ſecond Chapter of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:29260:67"/> his Booke of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> hee recounts at large, the ſenſuall thoughts, the earthly conceits of all ſuch Epicures and Atheiſts, <hi>Qui non ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcunt ſaeculum niſi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens,</hi> and at length hee windes up all on this clew; ſuch things doe they imagine, and goe aſtray, for their owne wickednes hath blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them; <hi>verſe</hi> 21. yea ſo blinded them, that as they live like beaſts, ſo they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin they ſhal dye like beaſts; that they ſhall not onely <hi>mori</hi> but <hi>per
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:29260:68"/> mori,</hi> dye like Oxen knocked on the head, that they ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilated, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they dance after this pipe, Let us eate and drinke for to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row we ſhall dye.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32.</note> Nay the Apoſtle hath it in the preſent tence <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>morimur,</hi> to not the ſenſuality of theſe wretches, who think that their ſoules and bodies ſhall bee quite extinguiſhed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>But on rotten joiſts is this fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation laid. Our bleſſed Saviour
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:29260:56"/> with the modeſty of truth hath long ſince confuted this bold &amp; broad fac'd hereſie of the Sadduces. Wee reade, <hi>Math.</hi> 22. That he put them to ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; the Originall is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hee brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their mouthes; which is a phraſe bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from fierce and ſtomackefull horſes, which beeing held in by a ſtrong bit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſubject perforce to the wil of the rider. Hee that ſpake as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver man ſpake ſo reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their doubts, and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:29260:57"/> diſſolved their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſmes, that they were tongue-ride, had not a word to returne upon him.</p>
               <p>It is farther obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable how our Savior in that place fits his Anſwer to the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniſts, and concludes moſt evidently againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by preſſing them with their owne prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalls. Concerning the Reſurrection of the dead he prooves it not out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, but drawes his Argument out of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>For wheras the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:29260:57"/> rejected all Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſave onely the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateuchi,</hi> Chriſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes with them in their owne Canons, and makes <hi>Moſes</hi> give them an anſwer, whoſe authority was ſacred with them.</p>
               <p>The Phariſees in their Doctrine were much neerer the truth than the Sadduces, for they confeſſed that there were Angels and Spirits, they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Saint <hi>Paul</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, that in the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:29260:58"/> Councell the one part were Saduces,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 23.6.</note> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Phariſees, cryed out of the hope [<hi>id eſt,</hi> of the reward expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed] and of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead I am called in queſtion; yet though theſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries had a branch of the Tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, they bowed the ſprig the wrong way; They taught that the ſoules of evill men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed departed into everlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but the ſoules, ſaid they, of good men by a kinde of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagorian
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:29260:58"/> tranſmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into other good mens bodies. Of which Opinion <hi>Herod</hi> may ſeeme to have beene; for when newes was brought him of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hee ſaid that <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt being be<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, was riſen againe; thinking that the ſoul of the Baptiſt was paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into the body of Ieſus? Hence againe aroſe the like diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opinions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our Savior, ſome ſaying hee was <hi>Elias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.14.</note> others <hi>Ieremias,</hi> as if Chriſts body had bin
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:29260:59"/> animated by the ſoule either of <hi>Iohn, Elias,</hi> or <hi>Ieremias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were a world to rake up the old errors of all ſuch as have drawn in the ſame line it were infinite to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the fond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of the Saturni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Baſilidians, and thoſe whom <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> calls <hi>Partiatios Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducaeorum,</hi> or Semi-Sadduces. But I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to ſet down fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies for truths, I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſpare that oyle: for as it was noted by ſome as a token of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:29260:59"/> Gods ſpeciall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> &amp; <hi>Pelagius</hi> the heretike ſhould come into the world much about one yeere, that the Antidote might bee contemporary with the poyſon: ſo truth in all ages hath beene juſtified by her children, and our Church hath ever found ſome Advocate to plead her cauſe, ſo that the gates of Hell (which <hi>Origen</hi> well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds to be blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming hereſies) ſhall never prevaile againſt it.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:29260:60"/>
               <p>And here may wee caſt a Dart at the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces and Epicures of our times, for theſe be not the names of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but of a diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, every Countrey may have a Sadduce, every Table an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This hereſie is every day brought on the ſtage, and is but <hi>vetus fabula per novos hiſtrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> the ſame play act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againe by other Actors.</p>
               <p>The palliated hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite that gives <hi>God</hi> the complement of a
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:29260:60"/> faſhionable profeſſion who weares Chriſts livery, but ſerves the Devill, is a Sadduce, all his holineſſe is but theatricall and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, a ſtage-devotion, he doth but play Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: by his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> his rough caſt counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance he deceives the world.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Moore.</note> It was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly ſpoken by him, who ſaid of a vitious Prieſt, that hee would not for any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the Creed, leſt he ſhould make him call the Articles of his Faith into queſtion,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:29260:61"/> 
                  <hi>Quis audiet illum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem, qui ſeipſum non audit?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that daily feeds on <hi>cibos deſiderij,</hi> whoſe luſhious appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite walkes from diſh to diſh, <hi>Et pittiſando totum conſumit diem,</hi> as if his ſoule (which ſome Philoſophers held) were made of ſalt, is an Epicure that digges his grave with his teeth, and adoreth <hi>Deum ſtercorarium,</hi> he makes his belly his God. This argument is too demonſtrative, it ſhall content mee
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:29260:61"/> onely to glance at the generality of ſo copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a theame. Surely this looſeneſſe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ariſeth from the ſelf-perſwaſion of the mortality of the ſoule; that is the <hi>Nilus,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this <hi>Crocodile</hi> is bred for as <hi>Tertullian</hi> well, <hi>Nemo tam carnaliter vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit quam qui negat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectionem carnis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the contrary, he whoſe mind is deeply ſeaſoned with a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our humane frailty, doth ſo live, <hi>Tanquam Ephemeridem Deo traditurus,</hi> every
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:29260:62"/> day beeing ready to give an account to his God; hee conſiders that this world, for all the World, is like a Globe of Chryſtall, which though it take the eye with variety, and delights of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, yet the glory thereof is but little and brittle.</p>
               <p>Wee reade in the <hi>Acts</hi> that <hi>Agrippa</hi> and <hi>Bernice</hi> came into the place where <hi>Pauls</hi> cauſe was to be heard,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 25.23.</note> with great pompe, it is in the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:29260:62"/> thus much, that the glory and pompe of this world, is but a phanſie, a dream. This life is but <hi>ſaeculi falſi vita</hi> (as the Heathen man ſpake) but the hope of the life im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall is the life of this hope mortall.</p>
               <p>In the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture phraſe, death is called a change, <hi>Iob</hi> 14. In the third of <hi>Iames</hi> we read of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> (as the word carrieth it) the wheele of our nature; this wheele turneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:29260:63"/> and daily turnes off ſome, and we know not how ſoon our turn will come. Our eſtate in this life is like the verticall Dyall which ſheweth neither our <hi>Ortum</hi> or <hi>Occaſum,</hi> our <hi>Geneſis</hi> or our <hi>Exodus,</hi> our comming into the world, or the time when we are to go out of it: But our eſtate in the life to come is like the Horizontall Dyall, upon which the Sun ſhineth alwayes, there ſhall the Sunne of righteouſneſſe for ever ſhine, and in his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:29260:63"/> light ſhall wee ſee light.</p>
               <p>I have dwelt long on this ſubject, and am loath to part with ſo ſweet a meditation; but leſt I ſtrike too much on the ſame ſtring, which is a fault in muſicke, I will like a skilfull Gardner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light your eyes with variety of objects, and in this maze ſhew an order in confuſion; and becauſe the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our faith are not only <hi>Credenda,</hi> but <hi>Credibilia,</hi> I will ſee what fruit I can pluck
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:29260:64"/> for our purpoſe, from the Tree of <hi>Pophiry,</hi> I will fetch ſome Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſchools, and give you a ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:29260:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Of many reſemblances in the booke of Nature of our Reſurrection.</head>
               <p>IF we borrow ſome Iewels from the Aegyptians, and ſearch the writings of prophane Authors, we ſhall often find ſome ſhadow of holy hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.<note place="margin">Plato Moſes alter Moſes Atticus.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> the divine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:29260:53"/> the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers (as it is obſerved by one, who ſweetly deſcants on the ſongs of Sion, which <hi>Ionas</hi> ſung in a ſtrange land, when he was impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a living tombe, within a Chryſtall cage) this <hi>Moſes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Athenians differeth but a little in deſcribing the Nature of the god-head, from that other <hi>Moſes,</hi> which was as I may ſo ſay <hi>(abſit invidia verbo)</hi> a <hi>Plato</hi> amongſt the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, each of them doth but a little vary
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:29260:53"/> the Article, The one writes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, He that is, the other <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, That that is; From whence wee may take up this note, when God had a purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale his eternity to <hi>Moſes,</hi> hee choſe to do it by a word, which being but one ſyllable amongſt the Greeks doth notwithſtanding ſignify and containe three times, that which is paſt, that which is preſent, that which is to come; all which are indiſtinct in God, becauſe hee is
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:29260:54"/> not changed, but is yeſterday, to day, and the ſame for ever more, for in Gods Grammer as it is wit tily ſaid, there are no lerters, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. no Nowne but <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> no Pronoune but <hi>Ipſe,</hi> no Verbe but <hi>Sum,</hi> no Adverbe but <hi>Nunc.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to leave genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and to returne to the head of our race where wee firſt began. In this point of reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſoule with the body, this Athenian Eagle hath ſoared higher than any other
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:29260:54"/> of the Philoſophers,<note place="margin">Anma Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicus.</note> for hee held that in the revolution of ſo many yeeres, men ſhould be in the ſame eſtate wherein they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which is obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawne from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; when wee ſhall bee in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math,</hi> 19 28.</note> as wee were in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The Principall Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary in nature, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator of reaſon, holds the immortality of the ſoule, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrong reaſons even from his own axiomes and rules of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy may bee derived
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:29260:55"/> to confirme the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body. For if wee admit the ſoule to bee immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, then it muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow that the body, as the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganon or inſtrument thereof bee revnited thereunto. The ſoule was not made to live to it ſelfe, but in the body, and reſteth not fully content ſo long as ſhe wanteth her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion. Secondly, the ſoule ſeparated from the body is imperfect, <hi>Et nulla res imperfecta eſt capax perfectae falici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:29260:55"/> Thirdly, <hi>Non eſt perpetuum quod eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra naturam;</hi> but it is contrary to the nature of a mans ſoule to be ſeparated from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſeing it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the perfecting act thereof; wherfore the Soule cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſeparated, but muſt neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the body.</p>
               <p>It is not my intent to leade my Reader in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Lycaeum</hi> of the Peripateticks, or the Gallery of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks, or the <hi>Tuſculatum</hi> of the Oratour. The
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:29260:56"/> ſeaſon of the yeere doth now invite us with <hi>Iſaack</hi> into the fields, and with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Aramathea</hi> into our gardens: And here (as it hath ever beene the guiſe of godly men from the beholding of worldly things to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thoughts, to turne the ſight of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſolemnity into a Schoole of Divinity, and from things they ſee here downeward, to make a proſpect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) whatſoever is preſented to our eyes, may be an Embleme
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:29260:68"/> to us of our reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How doth it feed us with delight, to view the trees apparel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with a freſh beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? to ſee,
<q>
                     <l>— The mealy mountaines late unſeene,</l>
                     <l>Change their white gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into luſty greene,</l>
                     <l>The gardens prancke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with their flowry buds,</l>
                     <l>The meades with graſſe, with leaves the naked woods.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For what is the Spring, but as <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> calleth it the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the yeere? and it is no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:29260:69"/> to reaſon, that man for whom all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things doe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhoote forth, wax freſh, ſpring and riſe againe, ſhould not have his ſpring and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing too.</p>
               <p>The whole creature doth write a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to give us com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in this point; but principally the Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Phenix that ſole bird of wonder;<note place="margin">The Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix.</note> never did the Roman Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors lye in their beds in greater ſtate, when in their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they were to bee burnt, and
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:29260:69"/> changed to Gods, then ſhe doth conſume her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in coſt, becauſe ſhee knowes ſhe ſhall bee revived. By all wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhe hath ever been held a type of our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reſurrection: In the 91. Pſalme it is ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, In the vulgar tranſlation wee reade it, hee ſhall flouriſh like the palme, but it may be tranſlated, hee ſhall flouriſh like the Phenix, for the greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, admitts of both ſignifications.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dies diei diſcipulus,</hi>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:29260:70"/> one day teacheth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and one night certifieth another, each day dieth into the night, and riſeth into the morning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, theſe viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of times, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions of ſeaſons, are but ſo many deaths and ſo many reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Homo eſt nummus Dei,</hi> Man is Gods coine ſtamped with his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Rulers, as of the Image of God, compareth the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to pictures drawne
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:29260:70"/> cleane through even to the feet; the middle ſort, to halfe pictures drawne to the girdle; the meaneſt to the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſort of pictures drawn but to the necke and ſhoulders: But all in ſome degree carry his Image, as well the poore penny, as the coine of gold. In theſe lively pictures of ours may wee ſee ſome ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, ſome reſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our future Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, doe not our nails pared, &amp; our haire being cut grow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? And if theſe
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:29260:71"/> dead parts of the body bee reſtored by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary power of God in nature, much more ſhall his mighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er reſtore the bodies of men; hath God given me the ſecurity of the very haires of my head, and ſhall I diſtruſt him for the raiſing of my body?</p>
               <p>Theſe and the like meditations are armor of proofe againſt the feare of death. <hi>Pulvis es, &amp; in pulverem rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris,</hi> is Mans Epitaph writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Gods own finger.—<hi>Libenter mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:29260:71"/> ſum, quiſim futurus immortalis,</hi> is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mans ſuſcription and reply.</p>
               <p>I might here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſgreſſion record what I find upon file, many memorable ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>Apothegmata me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientium,</hi> and <hi>noviſſima verba,</hi> the laſt breath of ſuch Seraphycall <hi>Zelots,</hi> as have gone to heaven, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with ſome ſentence of piety in their mouthes, with good words in their lips, and like ſo many dying ſwans have war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:29260:72"/> out their ſoules into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of God. But this field hath bin already reaped to my hand.</p>
               <p>Since an Angell ſate on our Saviours grave, and proclamed thoſe good tidings—<hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit non eſt hic,</hi> wee have added to our tombe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones too <hi>Hic jacet</hi>-this happy clauſe-<hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſurgendi;</hi> for wee know that the bodies of the dead are not loſt but layed up, that they doe not periſh but reſt in hope, that the ſepulchers are not
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:29260:72"/> gulfes to ſwallow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but repoſitaries to keep the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; therfore do the Germans wittily call the Church-yard Gods acker, becauſe the bodies are ſowne there to bee raiſed up againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Securus moritur qui ſcit ſe morte renaſci.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Soules take your reſt, whoſe ſoule in heavens at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A bleſt reunion of two loving friends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When Chriſt ſhall come with a <hi>Prodi La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zare,</hi> the graves ſhall ſet ope their marble
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:29260:73"/> doores; when the Ark-Angell ſhall ſound the trump of collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſcatter'd bones of the Saints ſhalbe gathered together with ſinewes, and thoſe ſinewes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated with fleſh, and that fleſh covered o're with skin, and by a new <hi>Metempſycoſis</hi> or rather <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuch as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> never dream'd of, the ſame ſoule ſhall reenter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame body.</p>
               <p>But of the perfect reſtauration of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, and glory of our ſoules, wee ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:29260:73"/> more largely in the cloſe of our medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
               <p>Before I unlade my ſhip, and put her into the creeke, before I lodge my colours, I ſhould collect ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by way of refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from the abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities that ariſe from the deniall of this truth. The bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle hath ſet them downe at large in his Epiſtle to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thians, to which moſt comfortable Chapter (wherein is ſtore of <hi>Manna,</hi> for the ſoule
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:29260:74"/> to feed on) I referre my Reader. To com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon each of thoſe texts were to ſet up a candle before the Sunne; many of them being plaine and eaſy to bee underſtood. I will only ſelect one period of harder con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and give you, the.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:29260:74"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Divers readings and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of thoſe words, <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>15.29.</hi> Elſe what ſhall they do which are baptized for the dead, Or [as others] baptized for dead, if the dead riſe not at all, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>SOME Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call wits (as the Advocates of <hi>Rome</hi>) have extracted from hence a proofe
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:29260:75"/> of their Purgatory; as <hi>Stapleton</hi> and that Franciſcane in the Treatiſe of the fiery Torrent;<note place="margin">Du Moulin in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fut. of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat. p. <hi>268.</hi>
                  </note> who diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the paſſage thus, what ſhall they doe that baptize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the dead; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound that which they have corrupted in this manner, To baptize ones ſelfe ſignifieth to doe laborious and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory workes for the dead, and withall wee muſt underſtand, that it is to fetch them out of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. How fruitfull is
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:29260:75"/> errour of abſurdities? But <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will not ſit on the skirts of this firy hil, ſince <hi>Nabuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> cannot interpret his owne dreame, nor the learnedſt of our Adverſaries cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>read us their owne rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, this <hi>Somnium Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachorum;</hi> nor reſolve us concerning this mathematicall and i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginary fire; either where it is, or what it is: This <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> hath been ſufficiently quenched by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Shilo,</hi> which have abundantly flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:29260:76"/> from the beſt pen of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> by the dead underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſinnes, which are dead workes; as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, why are they baptized for the aboliſhing of ſin whereby death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and which bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing removed, death ſhall prevaile no more.</p>
               <p>Others, as <hi>Claudius Guiliandus</hi> underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it of Martyrdome for the faith of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe our Saviour ſpeaking of ſuffering Martyrdome
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:29260:76"/> to the ambitious ſons of <hi>Zebede,</hi> ſaid, can ye be baptized with my baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Theſe Expoſitions are far fetched. In this and the like places of Scripture, we muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven have <hi>Oculos ad ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum:</hi> for the occaſion of ſpeaking is the beſt key to every ſpeech; we will therfore weave this web a little clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer.</p>
               <p>In the tranſlation and interpretation of theſe words Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vary. I will ſtrike the ſeverall flints, each
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:29260:77"/> of them may afford a ſparke to give ſome light.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, are tranſlated by ſome, baptized over the dead, as though it had beene the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſome to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize over the graves of the dead, to cheriſh their hope of reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. If it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to have beene ſo by any Hiſtory, this would at once decide all controverſies: But (as a moderne writer deſcanting upon this Expoſition of <hi>Luther</hi>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:29260:77"/> hath obſerved) none hath made mention of any ſuch thing, and if we looke into the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of Gods owne Record, we ſhall finde that places of much Water, were raither choſe to baptize in, as <hi>Iordan,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> is ſaid to have baptized by <hi>Enon</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Salim,</hi> becauſe there was much water there:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.23.</note> And S. <hi>Luke</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports that the great Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> went into the water &amp; came out of the water at his baptiſme, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.38, 39.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:29260:78"/>
               <p>Others thinke that the Apoſtle here ſeems to allude to the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cuſtome of the faithfull Iewes, who to ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the hope of the reſurrection, uſed to waſh the bodies of their dead, and then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to embalm them before they bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them. As though the Apoſtle would prove there is a reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body, from this cuſtome, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing ſhould bee in vaine. Though this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:29260:78"/> bee of ſome weight, yet it is not ſufficiently agreeable to the phraſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle here uſeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> (according to the explication of <hi>Epiphanius</hi> upon the Text) interpreteth the Apoſtles words, as though he ſhould rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the cuſtome of ſuch converts and beginners in Religion, as neglecting baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me over-long, yet when their death ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, made haſte to bee baptized that their bodies might be
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:29260:79"/> waſhed and cleanſed againſt the joyfull day of the Reſurrection. Though the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation bee not lightly to bee paſſed by, yet I cannot reſt in it, as in that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſhould make his Epicherema &amp; ground of his reaſon; and Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf, worthily condemneth them, that ſhould ſo deferre their baptiſme till their going out of this life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Iunius</hi> rich in languages, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till in diſtinguiſhing,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:29260:79"/> hath obſerved, that this particle <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, though it be uſually and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly tranſtlated <hi>[Super]</hi> may nevertheleſſe (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the uſe of the ſame both Greeke and Latin praepoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in Greeke and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin writers) bee taken here for [<hi>Praeter</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides] or in ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of [<hi>Inſuper</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over] as noting the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſme, in the Church, by a conſtant courſe, for the comfort of the living ſtill, like as it was
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:29260:80"/> found to bee of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable uſe to thoſe that were dead, ſo long as they were alive; as though the words of the Apoſtle were to be read thus, Elſe what doe they, which are baptized ſtill, or more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over and beſide thoſe that are already dead; becauſe otherwiſe it might bee inferred, that unleſſe the dead ſhould riſe againe, neither have the dead any fruit of Baptiſme abiding them, to wit in reſpect of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and ſo ſhall bee
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:29260:80" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſappointed of that which they looked for by faith; neither have the living any reaſon, at leaſt in reſpect of the body, why it ſhould bee continued amongſt them. And this may the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Apoſtle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. Elſe what ſhall they doe, that are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, [<hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are already dead] and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, why are they [namely the living be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alive] yet Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands this place of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:29260:81"/> a Sacramentall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, applyed unto ſome living man, in the name and behalfe of his friend dying without Baptiſme, out of a ſuperſtitious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thus conferred to one alive in the name of the deceaſed, might bee available for the other dying unbaptized; As if the Apoſtle did here wound the ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Corinthians with their owne quils, and prove the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead, from
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:29260:81"/> their owne erroneous practice, telling them in effect, that their uſuall, (but miſgroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) and ſuperſtitious cuſtome of baptizing the living were in vaine, if there were no Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Thus have I briefly ſet before your eyes, what curious threads have beene drawne by expert workmen from this woofe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Other Truth men herein have laboured, and we have entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their labours.</p>
               <p>I have here, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:29260:82"/> preſented a <hi>Caena dubia,</hi> let each man pleaſe his own pallat; If any ſhall demand my ſentence, <hi>(Etiam &amp; culices circumvolent cum apibus)</hi> I doe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſubſcribe to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation given by <hi>du Moulin,</hi> which (with ſubmiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) I take to bee proper and genuine; Nor do I obtrude this explicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as Magiſteriall, but leave him if this ſenſe ſatisfy not, to his father diſquiſition.</p>
               <p>The ſenſe of theſe
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:29260:82"/> words (ſaith he) muſt bee taken of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles intent. His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was to prove the Reſurrection, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hee implyeth Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, which in thoſe dayes was celebrated, (as may appeare in the monuments of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Hiſtory) by dipping and as it were diving,<note place="margin">Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg. cant. <hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi> col. <hi>234.</hi>
                  </note> by plon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the whole body in water, in token that wee are in death. And the comming forth of the water, repreſenteth the Reſurrection. S. <hi>Pauls</hi> meaning is, that
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:29260:83"/> this ſigne were in vaine if there were no Reſurrection, and that in vain we are baptized for dead, or as dead, and to repreſent unto us, that we be in death if there be no hope of the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>And in this ſenſe may wee underſtand the Greeke [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] to bee uſed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, as the Latin <hi>[Pro]</hi> is uſed in this and the like phraſe, <hi>[habere pro derelicto]</hi> for hee which is baptized ſhould bee baptized for dead, <hi>i. e.</hi> as one in
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:29260:83"/> a manner dead, even to dye more and more unto ſinne, but to love more and more to God: becauſe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is a token of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, the pawne and Image of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſtiles it, <hi>Et per regenerationem cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora noſtra Reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni gloriae inaugurantur.</hi> Therfore ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; are wee buried with Chriſt in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> (as <hi>Ignatius</hi> expounds the phraſe aright) beleeving in his death, wee are by
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:29260:84"/> baptiſme made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>And thus having endeavoured to cleare this obſcure text of the Apoſtle, I joine iſſue againe with my former Meditations, and will ſhew that.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:29260:84"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> The ſame bodies which we now have, ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored unto us in the ſame ſubſtance; They ſhall bee Immortall, Honourable, Glorious, Spirituall, Impaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</head>
               <p>THe end of our MEDITATIONS ſhall bee the meditation of our end, the contemplation of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:29260:85"/> another life is the Star which guides us from the Eaſt to the Weſt, from our Orient to our Occident, and brings us at length to the place where our Saviour is. We know that in every man there is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a naturall queru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſnes againſt death, but this is ſilenced with the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of our Reſurrection, by which wee learne, that death is better than life, becauſe a paſſage to a better life. Here wee grow
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:29260:85"/> up to a full vigour, and then wee decreaſe till we deceaſe: but when we ſhall aſcend above the wheele of time, where nothing but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity dwelleth, wee ſhall have ſuch an iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue from death, as ſhal never paſſe into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther death; there at firſt wee come to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſtature, &amp; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for ever, that life ſhall laſt as long as the Lord of life him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>But why doe I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt an Eagles flight with the wing of a
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:29260:86"/> wren? why doe I ſeeke to expreſſe that which cannot bee expreſſed? I will not goe beyond my line, for a diapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp; reſt to our ſong, for a pawſe, a period, an <hi>Amen.</hi> I will a little deſcant on that which I find ſet downe by the Apoſtle through the ſacred Scripture, but principally in that excellent Chapter, which we may call the Spring garden of our Reſurrection.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>As the Princely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> when hee ſweetly warbled on
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:29260:86"/> the glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of God, hath for the <hi>Amaebaeum</hi> &amp; bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to his ſong, For, his mercy endureth for ever; ſo that divine &amp; Extaticall Doctor of the Gentils (as if hee had beene the Apoſtle of the Reſurrection) makes this comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Doctrine, the matter of moſt of his Epiſtles, upon this ſtocke doth he ſeeme to plant the whole body of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>At the generall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurection<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.</note> the dead in
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:29260:87"/> Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt, the obſervation is, that the ſentence of Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution ſhall bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced before the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a <hi>venite</hi> come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mee, before an <hi>Ite,</hi> depart from mee God is loath to let his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bee predominant; Then (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) ſhall wee who live and remaine be caught up with them alſo in the clouds; the word in the Originall is paſſive, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wee ſhall bee raviſhed, ſo our ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and upgoing ſhall
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:29260:87"/> not bee by our owne power, but the power of God.</p>
               <p>Againe; This cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible muſt put on incorruption, and this mortall, muſt put on immortallity; not a corruptible or mortall at large, but <hi>hoc,</hi> this corruptible, this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. The blind men which our Saviour cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, received no new made eyes, but only ſight to the eyes they had before; The wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes ſon, &amp; <hi>Lazarus,</hi> roſe in the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in which they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:29260:88"/> Hee that was ſeene in the fleſh, ſhall bee ſeene of the fleſh, yea of this ſelfeſame fleſh, <hi>videbo mihi:</hi> Not the ſubſtance or linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our bodies ſhall be changed, but the qualities. When the Apoſtle ſaith, hee ſhall raiſe up our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bodies, hee ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them in reſpect of that which they are now, not in reſpect of that they ſhal be then: For in the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as he teſtifieth that had a prelibation of that glory) they ſhall
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:29260:88"/> bee raiſed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Immortall, not ſubject to any more diſeaſe or death, wee ſhall not ſtand in need of theſe ordinary helps of meates and drinks, by which our nature is preſerved, <hi>Chriſtus tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiens miniſtrabit nobis,</hi> and it ſhall bee our meate and drinke to do our Fathers will.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Glorious; The Iuſt ſhall ſhine like the Sunne in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, <hi>Et qualis tunc erit ſplendor animarum, quando ſolis habebit cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem lux corporum?</hi>
                  <pb n="817" facs="tcp:29260:89"/> And to confirme the verity and ſolidity of this glory, it ſhall not only be revealed unto us, but (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in nobis,</hi> in us, Ieruſalem as the Kings daughter is all glorious within.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Honourable; Every defective mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhall bee reſtored to its integrity <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhall not hault, <hi>Iſaac</hi> bee blind, nor <hi>Leah</hi> bleere-eyed, nor <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phihoſheth</hi> be lame; <hi>Hoc eſt credere, Reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem integram credere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Spirituall; I
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:29260:89"/> meane a body ſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, not that it ſhall looſe the dimenſions of a body, and pierce through any naturall body, as the light pierceth through the glaſſe, as the Papiſts ſay of the Body of Chriſt after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection by a penetrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of dimenſions; but becauſe without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction they ſhall obey the motions of the Spirit beſides the glorified ſtate &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition it then be in.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Impaſſionate; Free from ſuch paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:29260:90"/> as may hurt, and offend, but not from the paſſion of Ioy, the joy of the ſoule ſhall bee the ſoule of Ioy.</p>
               <p>Other particulars I ceaſe to enquire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to deliver them, and in the ſilence of the Holy Ghoſt I will not be curious. I will not winde my ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a laborynth, where the happieſt wit may loſe it ſelfe. If the Diſciple that leaned on our Saviours breſt, (his <hi>Legatus à latere,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:29260:90"/> qui eſinu Domini biberat myſteria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.17.</note> from out of the boſome of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter dranke deepe of the heavenly wiſdom) brake off his Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with a <hi>Nemo ſcit,</hi> needes muſt I take up here a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Quis ad haec idoneus;</hi> needs muſt I leave my Reader with a <hi>Theologia negativa,</hi> a negative Divinity, or divine ignorance, and tell what is not in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>The plumage of the Cyſtrian Swanne appeares more white when 'tis oppos'd to
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:29260:91"/> the Ravens blackneſſe, and wee may better conjecture at the joies above, if wee conſider the miſeries on earth.</p>
               <p>In this world are a world of troubles; <hi>non habet is hic requië,</hi> ſaith the Prophet; Reſt and Glory, Glory and reſt, are two things that meete not here; the glorious life is not the moſt quiet, and the quiet life is for the moſt part inglorious.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sublunary tranſitory</l>
                  <l>Are as barres in th'armes of Glory.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Riches and Honor
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:29260:91"/> like <hi>Abſalons</hi> Mule do ſometime leave their Maſter in extremity.</p>
               <p>A conſideration, which if wel digeſted, would gather our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided thoughts, and rouze up our ſoules, <hi>quae ſurſum quaerere, quae ſurſum ſapere,</hi> to ſeeke firſt the Kingdome of Heaven, and then wee know <hi>caetera adijcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> and indeed when heaven is once named all worldly things are but, &amp;c. not worthy mentioning.</p>
               <p>It is obſerved by thoſe that are skild in
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:29260:92"/> the holy tongue,<note place="margin">Deus eſt centrum quietati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum.</note> that in the ſacred name <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi> are none but <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terae-quieſcentes,</hi> myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally implying thus much unto us, that God is the God of reſt, in whoſe preſence (as the Prophet ſings) there is joy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11</note> and fulnes of ioy, and fulneſſe of it for evermore.</p>
               <p>When once we ſhal be planted in that cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall paradice, there ſhall no apple of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention grow between God and us. It is <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzens</hi> note upon that divine Anthemne
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:29260:92"/> of three parts (which Saint <hi>Luke</hi> the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt and Pſalmiſt of the new Teſtament,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 2.14.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords) <hi>Pugnas &amp; diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia neſcire Deum &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos,</hi> no broiles, no brables in Heaven.</p>
               <p>There ſhall the ſoule bee ſatisfied in all her deſires, there ſhall bee no Actuall or Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall evill; no Actuall, becauſe grace being conſummate in the Saints excludes al ſin; No Potentiall, for they being confirmed in goodneſſe cannot ſinne. There ſhall bee
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:29260:93"/> no ſorrow, nor teares which are the effects of ſorrow, thoſe rivers of our eyes ſhall bee dried up; There ſhall be no more death, for <hi>Reſurrectio eri<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mors mortis;</hi> At that Iubile of glory <hi>victus vincet,</hi> the Conqueror ſhall bee diſarmed, and wee whom death hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come death.</p>
               <p>And now having ſung deaths Epitaph, &amp; ſounded the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I retreit, This <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhall bee my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; were my Inke
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:29260:93"/> nectar, or my pen take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the wing of an Angell, I could not ſet forth to the life the joyes of the life immortall.</p>
               <p>This caſteth me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an extaſis, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me imagine ſome great matter I cannot well expreſſe, what! Silence ſhall bee my Eloquence; what I comprehend I will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, and what I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend not I will more admire.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="188" facs="tcp:29260:94"/>
            <head>A Peroration to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THus have I wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked about Sion, and viewed the bulwarks thereof: I have ſhewed the ſtrength and munition of this Fort of Faith. In a plaine and ſhort way <hi>(nec breuius potui nec apertius)</hi> I have meditated ſomewhat one this ſweet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Article of our Creed.</p>
            <p>Expect more generous wine from old vine-trees; for reſolutions of ſacred
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:29260:94"/> riddles and deepe myſteries of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, conſult with ſuch, whoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trade is Divinity, with thoſe cunning <hi>Bezaliels,</hi> which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually digging in the precious gemmes of the holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>And now having caſt my Mite into the publike treaſury, having made my thoughts legible, and ſent them, <hi>in dias luminis a<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> This little Manuall <hi>(habent ſua fata libelli)</hi> muſt either ſtand or fall, at the uncerteinty of my Readers Iudgment.</p>
            <p>I doe not emboſome ſuch a Mountebanoke opinion, as to ſet the garland on my owne worke, I dare not arrogate to my ſelfe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rachnes motto (mihi ſoli de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo)</hi> and boaſt that I have ſpun
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:29260:95"/> this thread out of mine owne bowels, No I will freely confeſſe (it were meere ingratitude ſhould I not acknowledge it) <hi>Nihil egi ſine Theſeis,</hi> where I liked the water of other mens wells I have drunke deepe.</p>
            <p>I will therefore (with <hi>Lyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis</hi>) rejoice in this, that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver what I have learned, not what I invented, I have feld much wood out of other mens groves wherewith to build, but (as one ſpake in the like caſe) I have ſo hewed it, and ſquared it, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed it with my owne phraſe and my own methode, that the Authors, though good Enditers, can hardly bring in evidence of theft againſt me.</p>
            <pb n="291" facs="tcp:29260:95"/>
            <p>If this Enchiridion, or my <hi>vade Mecum,</hi> ſhall meete with a faire and candid interpretation from the Ingenuous, the file may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance bee drawne over it againe; Not that I hunt after the fume of vaine glory (what but an Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an eare will ſucke-in ſuch breath) but becauſe our ſecond thoughts are commonly more refined, and meditation like the wind gathers ſtrength in proceeding.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb n="192" facs="tcp:29260:96"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 28. the quotation in marg. <hi>juxta fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> hath reference to <hi>Damaſcen</hi> in pag. 29. p. 62 l. 8 for ſuperſt. reade ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 70. l. 4. for not only. r. both. 77. l. 6. r. worke is effected. 80. l. 4. r. his p<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erog. 82. l. 15 r. made man. 89. l. 8. r. life only. 96 l. 13. for <hi>fidem.</hi> r. <hi>ſpem.</hi> 99. l. 6. r. they that. 121. l. 10. r. heare him repeat. l. 17. leſt it. 133. l. 13. of nature. 144. l. 11 r. added on 145. l 12. for Soules. r. Bones. 167. l. 3. for love. r. liue. 189. l. 6. for. gemmes. r. mines.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29260:96"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
